In this lecture, let's answer the question.
How is JavaScript code executed?
We already know that it happens in a call stack
in the engine, but let's dig a bit deeper now.
And let's start
by supposing that our code was just finished compiling.
Just in the way that we learned in the last lecture.
So the code is now ready to be executed.
What happens then,
is that a so-called global execution context is created
for the top-level code.
And top-level code is basically code that is not
inside any function.
So again, in the beginning
only the code that is outside of functions will be executed.
And this makes sense, right?
Functions should only be executed when they are called.
And actually we saw this happening already
in our pig game project.
So there we had an init function,
which initialized our entire project
but in order to actually initialize the game
the first time that the page loaded,
we needed to call that function immediately
in our top-level code.
And so that's what I mean here.
But anyway, we can also see
what top-level code is in this example here.
So this name variable declaration
is clearly top-level code right?
And therefore it will be executed
in the global execution context.
Next, we have two functions, one expression,
and one declaration.
So these will also be declared,
so that they can be called later.
But the code inside the functions,
will only be executed when the functions are called.
Okay, so we know that a global execution context
is created for top-level code.
But now what exactly is an execution context?
Well, an execution context is an abstract concept.
But I define it basically as an environment
in which a piece of JavaScript is executed.
It's like a box that stores all the necessary information
for some code to be executed.
Such as local variables or arguments passed into a function.
So, JavaScript code always runs inside an execution context.
And to make this a bit more intuitive
let's imagine you order a pizza at a takeaway.
So usually that pizza comes in a box right?
And it might also come
with some other stuff that is necessary
for you to eat a pizza such as cutlery or a receipt,
so that you can actually pay for the pizza before eating it.
So, in this analogy,
the pizza is the JavaScript code to be executed,
and the box is of course the execution context
for our pizza.
And that's because eating the pizza happens inside the box
which is then the environment for eating pizza.
The box also contains cutlery and the receipt,
which are necessary to eat a pizza
or in other words, to execute the code, okay?
I hope that made sense,
and to made the concept of execution context
a little bit more clear.
Now, in any JavaScript project, no matter how large it is,
there is only ever one global execution context.
It's always there as the default context,
and it's where top-level code will execute.
And speaking of execute,
now that we have an environment
where the top-level code can be executed,
it finally is executed.
And there is not a lot to say about the execution itself.
It's just the computer CPU processing
the machine code that it received.
Okay, and once this first code,
so the top-level of code is finished,
functions finally start to execute as well.
And here is how that works.
For each and every function call,
and you execution context will be created
containing all the information that is necessary
to run exactly that function.
And the same goes for methods, of course,
because they're simply functions
attached to objects remember?
Anyway, all these execution contexts together,
make up the call stack that I mentioned before.
But more on that in a second.
Now, when all functions are done executing,
the engine will basically keep waiting
for callback functions to arrive
so that it can execute these.
For example, a callback function associated
with a click event.
And remember, that it's the event loop who provides
these new callback functions
as we learned in the last lecture.
All right.
So we know now what an execution context is,
but don't really know what it's made of.
So, what's inside of it?
And so let's find that out next.
And the first thing that's inside any execution context
is a so-called variable environment.
In this environment,
all our variables and function declarations are stored,
and there is also a special arguments object.
This object contains,
as the name says all the arguments that were passed
into the function that the current execution context
belongs to.
Because remember each function
gets its own execution context
as soon as the function is called.
So basically all the variables
that are somehow declared inside a function,
will end up in its variable environment.
However, a function can also access variables
outside of the function.
And we have already seen that in action
throughout this course,
especially in the projects of the previous section.
And this works because of something called the scope chain.
And we will learn all about scoping
and the scope chain later in the section.
But for now, what you need to know
is that the scope chain basically consists of
references to variables that are located
outside of the current function.
And to keep track of the scope chain,
it is stored in each execution context.
Finally, each context also gets a special variable
called the this keyword.
And once more, there is a special lecture
just about the this keyword later in the section.
Okay.
Now, the content of the execution context,
so variable environment, scope chain
and this keyword is generated in a so-called creation phase.
Which happens right before execution.
And now just one final
but very important detail that we need to keep in mind,
is that execution contexts belonging to arrow functions,
do not get their own arguments keyword,
nor do they get the this keyword, okay?
So, basically arrow functions
don't have the arguments object
and the this keyword.
Instead, they can use the arguments object,
and the this keyword
from their closest regular function parent.
And this is an extremely important detail to remember
about arrow functions and we will come back to it later.
So these are the things
that are necessary to run each function
as well as the code in the top-level.
Now behind the scenes, it's actually even more complex
but I think we're fine like this, aren't we?
And now let's actually try to simulate the creation phase
for this code example here.
So, as you hopefully know, by now,
we will get one global execution context
and one for each function.
So one for the first function,
and one for the second function.
In the global context,
we have the name variable declaration,
the first and second function declarations,
as well as the X variable declaration.
For the functions, the variable environment
will literally contain all the code
of a particular function.
Now the value of X is marked as unknown here,
because this value is the result
of the first function that we didn't run yet.
But we will simulate this in the next slide.
Now, technically none of these values actually become known
during the creation phase, but only in the execution phase.
So this is not 100% accurate here,
but it's just to illustrate
how these execution contexts work.
Okay? So just keep that in mind.
Anyway, now in the first function,
we have the a variable set to 1 and the b variable
which once again requires a function call
in order to become known.
Finally, the variable environment of the second function,
contains the C variable set to 2,
and since this is a irregular function,
so not an arrow function, it also has the arguments object.
And this object is an array,
which contains all the arguments that were passed
into the function when it was called.
In this case, as you can see, that's 7 and 9.
Quite simple right?
Well, it's simple because this is an extremely small
amount of code.
But now imagine there are hundreds of execution contexts
for hundreds of functions.
How will the engine keep track
of the order in which functions we're called?
And how will it know where it currently is
in the execution?
Well, that's where the call stack finally comes in.
And remember that the call stack,
together with the memory heap,
makes up the JavaScript engine itself.
But what actually is the call stack?
Well, it's basically a place where execution contexts
get stacked on top of each other,
in order to keep track
of where we are in the programs execution.
So the execution context that is on top of the stack,
is the one that is currently running.
And when it's finished running,
it will be removed from the stack,
and execution will go back
to the previous execution context.
And using the analogy from before,
it is as if you bought pizzas with some friends.
Each friend has a pizza box, and then you put the boxes
on top of each other, forming a stack,
in order to keep track, which pizza belongs to each friend.
Now, all this sounds a bit abstract, doesn't it?
And so to demonstrate how the call stack works,
let's walk through this code example together,
so that I can show you exactly what happens.
So, once the code is compiled,
top-level code will start execution.
And then as we learned in the beginning of the lecture,
a global execution context will be created
for the top-level of code, right?
So this is where all the code outside of any function
will be executed.
And what happens with this execution context?
That's right, it will be put in the call stack.
And since this context is now at the top of the stack,
it is the one where the code is currently being executed.
So, let's continue now with this execution.
So here, there is a simple variable declaration.
And then the first and the second functions are declared.
So nothing fancy, but that's just how normal top-level code
gets executed.
But then, in the last line
is where things start to get interesting.
Here, we declare the X variable,
with the value that is gonna be returned
from calling the first function.
And so let's actually call that function.
Now what happens immediately when a function is called?
Well, it gets its own execution context
so that it can run the code that's inside its body.
Perfect.
And what happens to the context?
Well, again it is put in the call stack,
on top of the current context,
and so it's now the new current execution context.
Great.
So, let's continue.
So we have yet another simple variable declaration here,
and this variable will of course be defined
in the variable environment
of the current execution context,
and not in the global context, right?
Then right in the next line, we have another function call.
So, let's call that function and move there.
And as you guessed a new execution context
was created right away for this second function.
And once more, it is pushed
onto the call stack and becomes the new active context.
Now what's important to note here is that the execution
of the first function has now been paused, okay?
So again, we are running the second function now
and in the meantime, no other function is being executed.
The first function stopped at this point
where the second function was called
and will only continue as soon
as this second function returns.
And it has to work this way because remember,
JavaScript has only one thread of execution.
And so it can only do one thing at a time.
Okay? Never forget that.
Now, moving to the next line, we have a return statement
meaning that the function will finish its execution.
So, what does that mean for the call stack?
Well, it basically means
that the function's execution context,
will be popped off the stack
and disappear from the computer's memory.
At least that's what you need to know for now
because actually the popped off execution context
might keep living in memory.
But more about that later in the course.
Anyway, what happens next,
is that the previous execution context, will now be back
to being the active execution context again.
And so let's also go back to where we were
before in the code.
And I hope that by now,
you start to see how the call stack really keeps track
of the order of execution here.
Without the call stack,
how would the engine know which function
was being executed before?
It wouldn't know where to go back to, right?
And that's the beauty of the call stack.
It makes this process almost effortless.
So I like to use the analogy
of the call stack being like a map
for the JavaScript engine.
Because the call stack ensures
that the order of execution never gets lost.
Just like a map does, at least if you use it correctly.
All right.
So, we returned from the second function,
or back in the first function
where we have this calculation,
and then finally this first function also returns.
And so here the same as before happens.
So the current execution context gets popped off the stack,
and the previous context is now the current context
where code is executed.
In this case, we're back to the global execution context
and the line of code where the first function
was first called.
So here, the return value is finally assigned to X
and the execution is finished.
Now the program will now actually stay in this state
for forever until it is eventually really finished.
And that only happens like when we close the browser tab,
or the browser window.
Only when the program is really finished like this,
is when the global execution context
is also popped off the stack.
And this is in a nutshell how the call stack works.
So hopefully it makes sense now that we say
that Java script code runs inside the call stack.
And actually it is more accurate to say
that code runs inside of execution contexts
that are in the stack.
But the general point is that code runs in the call stack,
which is of course true.
Great.
Next up, we will learn some more
about the variable environment,
and how variables are created.
So stay tuned for the next video.